Guide to the Marita Golden papers, 1969-2017 MS2235
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Marita Golden papers
1969-2017
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Golden, Marita
MS2235
10.5 Linear Feet
The material in this collection consists of manuscript drafts, galleys, and research notes related to the work of author and teacher Marita Golden. The material dates from 1969-2017.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marita Golden, 2007 (Accession 2007.062) Gift of Marita Golden, 2016 (Accession 2016.095) Gift of Marita Golden, 2017 (Accession 2017.021) Gift of Marita Golden, 2018 (Accession 2018.005) Gift of Marita Golden, 2018 (Accession 2018.045)
Historical or Biographical Note
Marita Golden, local author and teacher, founder of both the Hurston/Wright Foundation and the African American Writers Guild, has spent more than 30 years teaching at many universities including George Mason and American University.
Her fiction includes the novel After, Long Distance Life, (a best-seller, cited as a "Best Book of the Year" by The Washington Post), A Woman's Place, And Do Remember Me, and The Edge of Heaven. In the genre of nonfiction, Marita Golden has edited two anthologies, Wild Women Don't Wear No Blues: Black Women Writers on Love, Men and Sex; and with writer Susan Shreve, Skin Deep: Black and White Women on Race and the book Don't Play in the Sun. As a memoirist and essayist, Golden has authored Migrations of the Heart, Saving Our Sons: Raising Black Children in a Turbulent World, and A Miracle Everyday: Triumph and Transformation in the Lives of Single Mothers.
All of Marita Golden's texts are widely read and used in college courses that represent a wide range of disciplines, from literature, African American Studies, and anthropology, to Women's Studies.
As a teacher of writing, Marita Golden has held appointments at George Mason University, and Virginia Commonwealth University, where she served as a member of the MFA Graduate Creative Writing programs. She has also taught at Emerson College, The University of Lagos (Nigeria), Roxbury Community College.
Marita Golden has lectured on the topic of literature, women's studies, African-American Studies and African American literature nationally and internationally. She has read from her work and held writer-in-residence positions at many schools, including Brandeis University, the University of the District of Columbia, Hampton University, Simmons College, Columbia College, William and Mary, Old Dominion University and Howard University. She has also been a guest on the Oprah Winfrey Show, and has appeared on ABC's Primetime Live. Articles and essays by Marita Golden have appeared in Essence Magazine, The New York Times and The Washington Post.
Marita Golden founded and served as the first president of the Washington-D.C. based African American Writers Guild. Since 1990 she has headed the Zora Neale Hurston/Richard Wright Foundation, which presents the nation's only national fiction award for college writers of African descent and an annual summer writer's workshop for Black writers, Hurston/Wright Writers' Week, as well as the Hurston/Wright Legacy Award for published Black writers.
Among the awards Marita Golden has received in recognition of her writing career and her work as a literary cultural worker are The 2002 Distinguished Service Award from the Authors Guild, The 2001 Barnes and Noble Writers for Writers Award presented by Poets and Writers; an honorary Doctorate from the University of Richmond; induction into the International Hall of Fame for Writers of African Descent at the Gwendolyn Brooks Center at Chicago State University; Woman of the Year Award from Zeta Phi Beta; and a Distinguished Alumni Award from American University. Her novel AFTER received 2007 Fiction Award from the Black Caucus of the American Library Association and was nominated for Outstanding Literary Work Fiction by the 38th annual NAACP Image Awards.
Marita Golden holds a B.A. from American University in American Studies and English and an Masters Degree from the Graduate School of Journalism at Columbia University. She is writer in residence at the University of the District of Columbia.
(from the biography at the website: http://www.maritagolden.com/index.html)
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains hand-written and typed drafts, edited drafts, galley proofs, articles, audiocassettes, interviews, and research notes related to the literary career of Marita Golden. The material is dated from 1969-2017, although most of the manuscript drafts are not dated.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Book drafts and research materials, Articles, Non-book writings, Speeches and talks, and Hurston/Wright Foundation.
Separated Materials
The following two books were added to the Special Collections stacks: "Word Nation" and "The Wide Circumference of Love"
Washington (D.C.); Writings; Audiocassettes; Literature; African Americans
- Book drafts and research materials, 1983-2007; MS2235 Series 1; 6.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains drafts both hand-written and typed, galley proofs, research notes, and interviews for several books written by Marita Golden. These books include among others After, Saving our Sons, Migrations of the Heart, Life at a Distance, Wild Women, A Woman's Place, and The Edge of Heaven.
  Arrangement
  Alphabetically by publication. Folders with titles that do not reference a specific novel are at the end.
  - And Do Remember Me (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - And Do Remember Me: uncorrected proof, 06-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - And do remember me uncorrected proof, 1992; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - And do remember us: A Historical and Psychoanalytical analysis of Marita Golden's novel and do remember me by Sarah Ann Heilbron, 1996; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - And do remember me handwritten version, Undated; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - And do remember me handwritten version II, Undated; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - And do remember me drafts, Undated; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - After: 2nd person "you" version (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - After: composition order [1/2], 01/06/2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - After: composition order [2/2], 01/06/2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - After: file matter from Doubleday Broadway Publishing Group [1/2], 08/16/2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - After: file matter from Doubleday Broadway Publishing Group [2/2], 08/16/2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - After: first pass reader's set [1/2], 01/26/2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - After: first pass reader's set [2/2], 01/26/2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - After: confirmation pages full set [1/2], 03/16/2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - After: confirmation pages full set [2/2], 03/16/2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - After: notes and research [1/11] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - After: notes and research [2/11] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - After: notes and research Harlem Black Cops [3/11], 10/2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - After: notes and research Lonise Bias [4/11], 10/2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - After: notes and research real estate [5/11] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - After: notes and research Sonny Catoe [6/11] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - After: notes and research Brian Jordan [7/11] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - After: notes and research Mark Moore [8/11] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - After: notes and research Dr. Beverly Anderson [9/11] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - After: notes and research Novel [10/11] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - After: notes and research novel revisions carson [11/11] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - After: draft (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - After: mss copy edited by my editor Janet Hill up to page 251 [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - After: mss copy edited by my editor Janet Hill up to page 251 [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - After: edited version [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - After: edited version [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - After: early draft partial (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - After: final draft [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - After: final draft [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - All Our Sons a book proposal by Marita Golden (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book covers for books by Marita Golden (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Calling My Name draft, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Chapter drafts - Father's House, 1999; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Charlotte (A Miracle Every Day), 1999; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Daniel draft, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: proposal (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: film [1/10] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: color struck by Zora [2/10] (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: one [3/10] (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: two [4/10] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: three [5/10] (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: interviews [6/10] (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: chapter 4 Mirror on the Wall [7/10] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: chapter 5 Sisters under the skin [8/10] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: chapter 7 Far from home [9/10] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color notes: chapter 8 Reading dark/ reading light [10/10] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: notes [1/2] (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: notes [2/2] (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Don't Play in the Sun [1/2], 10/17/2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Don't Play in the Sun [2/2], 10/17/2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Don't Play in the Sun: color complex exam questions Texas, 12/2005-02/2006 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Edge of Heaven: bound galley, 01-1998 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - The Edge of Heaven [1/2], 1999; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - The Edge of Heaven [2/2], 1999; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - The Edge of Heaven draft, 1999; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - The Edge of Heaven draft, 1999; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - The Edge of Heaven draft, 1999; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Novel draft - The Edge of Heaven, 1999; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Long Distance Life: long hand draft (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Long Distance Life: notes and research (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Long Distance Life (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Long Distance Life: "Way of the New World" (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Long Distance Life (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Long Distance Life: galley [1/2] (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Long Distance Life: galley [2/2] (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Long Distance Life draft [1/2], 1989; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Long Distance Life draft [2/2], 1989; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Long Distance Life: draft [1/2] (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Long Distance Life: draft [2/2] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Long Distance Life: articles (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Long Distance Life uncorrected proof, 1989; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Michael Lindsey (A Miracle Every Day), 1999; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Michael Lindsey (A Miracle Every Day), 1999; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Michael Lindsey - Resilient Characteristics, 1995-1996; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Migrations of the Heart: page proof (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Migrations of the Heart: early version (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Migrations of the Heart: edited proof [1/2] (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Migrations of the Heart: edited proof [2/2] (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Migrations of the Heart: articles (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Migrations of the Heart: book proposal "coming home an personal memoir" (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Migrations of the Heart: early draft (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Migrations of the Heart: draft [1/2] (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Migrations of the Heart: draft [2/2] (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Migrations of the Heart uncorrected proof, 1983; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Migrations of the Heart final galley proof, 1983; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - A Miracle Every Day draft, 1999; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - A Miracle Every Day, 1999; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - A Miracle Every Day: bound galley, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal resource book, Undated; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Notes from the Frontlines of Motherhood by Marita Golden (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Saving Our Sons: early draft (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Saving Our Sons: notes (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Saving Our Sons: interviews with Terrance Brown and Ella Ross (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Saving Our Sons: articles and reviews (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Saving Our Sons: publicity (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Saving Our Sons: nearing final draft (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The Way Home first draft 100 pages, Undated; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - The Way Home drafts loose pages [1/2], Undated; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - The Way Home drafts loose pages [2/2], Undated; Series 1 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Wild Women: notes (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - A Woman's Place: draft (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - A Woman's Place: draft [1/2] (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - A Woman's Place: draft [2/2] (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - A Woman's Place: unbound galley [1/2] (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - A Woman's Place: unbound galley [2/2] (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - A Woman's Place: uncorrected proof, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Wild Women Don't Wear Blues: Black Women Writers on Love, Men and Sex: uncorrected proof, 08-1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Wild Women Don't Wear No Blues, 1993; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Word Nation (Published), 2011; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Draft of unknown publication, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Draft, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Draft, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Draft, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Draft, Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Draft of Chapter 2 of "A Mother's Love", Undated; Series 1 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Draft of first novel (unpublished) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - [drafts], Undated; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Handwritten drafts, Undated; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Handwritten drafts/notes, Undated; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Handwritten notes, Undated; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Handwritten notes, Undated; Series 1 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Original folder title "Novel", Undated; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Original folder title "Novel", Undated; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Original folder title "writing essay", Undated; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Original folder title "second draft of part one proofed/edited", Undated; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Notebook, Undated; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Novel pages/schedule, Undated; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Original manuscript [unknown title], Undated; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - [Prologue and loose papers], Undated; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Proposal Book # 4, Undated; Series 1 (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Articles, 1969-2007; MS2235 Series 2; 1.75 Linear Feet
  This series contains articles written by and about author Marita Golden. These articles date from 1971-19969
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Album of articles, 1969-1974; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Articles from an album, 1971- circa 1986 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Articles under name Bernette Golden, 1973-1997; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Articles under the name Bernette Golden, 1974-1994; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Articles by and about Marita Golden, 1980-1990 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Articles and reviews, 1983-1992; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Articles on Marita Golden, 1983-1999; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Interviews with Marita Golden, 1986; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Writings/articles some under pen name Bernette, 1989-2001; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1994-2004; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Reviews, 1995-1997; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Dialogue Magazine, 2000; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - NY Times Color Article, 2004; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "After" Reviews, 2006; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Articles/writings, 2007; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Non-Book Writings, 2002-2009; Series 3; .5 Linear Feet
  Arranged chronologically with undated folders at the end.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents by Marita Golden that are non-book or unpublished works. The material dates from 2002-2009, but many of the items are undated.
  - Beverly Anderson, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Colorbook notes (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Color Book Interview Book #2, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Color Complex, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Copshock, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Don't Play in the Sun, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Early Poems, Undated; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Major Summers, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Sonny Catoe, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Steven Sunday, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Terrance Brown, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - WPFW It's About Color, 03/21/2002; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Don't Play in the Sun by Marita Golden performed by Michelle Hurst, 2004; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    General note
    This is a book on CD
  - After by Marita Golden performed by Ezra Knight, 2006; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Perez Story, 2007; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - "I Want to Write" E-Book, 2009; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript of "Living Out Loud", Undated; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Essays, Undated; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 15)
- Speeches, talks, and programs, 1983-2010; Series 4
  This series contains documents pertainting to awards recieved and speeches given by Marita Golden. The documents are dated between 1983-2010, though some are undated.
  - Coming Together [VHS WBZ-TV program], 1983 April 17; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Beyond the Dream V VHS, 1993; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, 1995-1996; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Speeches/Talks, 2005-2012; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Israel Fulbright Speech, 2009; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Dominion Power-Strong Men & Women Award Ceremony, 2005; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Awards/Programs, 2006-2010; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Black Caucus Award, 2007; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Zora Speech, Undated; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Hurston/Wright Foundation, 1992-2007; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet
  This series includes magazines, awards, articles and banners related to the Hurston/Wright Foundation. The items date between 1997-2007, though some items are undated.
  - Magazine and program, 1992-2006; Series 5 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Hurston Wright Foundation, 1990-2006; Series 5 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Hurston/Wright Foundation, 2002-2007; Series 5 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Annual Hurston Wright Legacy Award Banner (Box 15)
    General
    There are two banners and a tassel in this box. All related to the Hurston Wright Foundation.